Chapter 1: Tom Riddle and Albus Dumbledore

Authors Notes:

This is loosely based on HPMOR's Tom Riddle and the mechanics and facts of the story.

However I elaborate and change known facts as I see fit for the sake of the story. I also borrow facts and details from the original HP series.

Chapter One - Tom Riddle and Albus Dumbledore

Tom stood in the pitch dark of his private dorm. Having extinguished the glowing torches on the wall of his room, he carefully set his wand on his desk, and then closed his eyes. He deftly navigated around his desk and past his bed into the center of the room. How many times did I have to practice this dance before I achieved perfection? He wondered idly, smiling to himself. The average wizard would never even consider that they may have to fight blind someday; the average wizard was a fool.

The most basic artificial light charm was so easy that Tom didn't even need to say the incantation to brightly light a room, when he held his wand. So there should be no reason to hold his wand. After all, Tom could cast so many basic charms (and even more complicated ones) without a wand or word. He had no idea why this one was giving him so much trouble, but he was perversely glad of the challenge. Eventually he'd figure it out, and in learning he may glean some other valuable insight into magic. Still, such a simple spell should just come naturally to him at this point! It never failed to annoy him, slightly, when he actually had to work to perform magic.

He focused on intention: create a light, contained to this room. He drew up the little bit of his own raw magic that would be needed to cast the spell and let the incantation pass through the back of his mind and echo there. Normally at this point he would wave his wand, and the room would seem to have its own sun, but without it he had to think. He mentally shaped his magic around his intention. Feeling his magic flowing through him, he guided it into a specific shape: an orb encompassing the intention, then carefully poured just a little extra force into it, to make up for the lack of wand. As he opened his eyes, he forced his body's magic to extend out into the room like a ghastly invisible third arm that held the spell in its fist. The room lit up with a dim green light for a moment or two. Tom could make out the desk across from him. The light faded almost as quickly as it came. The desk disappeared into darkness again.

Tom's brief smile turned down. That had been the same as his previous attempts, green light and all. When he cast it with a wand, it was a brilliant white light. Maybe there was some fundamental difference in this charm's mechanics compared to most other basic charms? There had to be. Well, Tom would figure it out in time; this was a puzzle that must be completed at all costs. Figuring out that small secret behind a basic lighting charm could very well provide the insight to improve a powerful ritual someday. Tom never took any small insight for granted. An obscure fact about one spell here, and observation of another curse there, sometimes that was all it took for a clever wizard to make a connection and use that to revolutionize some other technique...

Tom closed his eyes to try the spell again, but a brief warning flashed in the back of his mind. It was somebody approaching his door, according to his rudimentary room ward. Sighing, Tom flicked his wrist and his wand flew into his hand as if it had always been there. He shifted position, balancing himself with his wand at the ready, drawing up power to cast any number of dangerous curses. He waited a few seconds, fancying that the door would be blasted from the hinges by some arcane magic for a change, before hearing the soft knock of knuckles on wood.

Except it wasn't that soft, was it? It seemed more firm and insistent. He flicked his wrist; his wand disappearing into the holster down his sleeve, then approached the door. Of course it wouldn't be an attack, not in the castle, not now. Yet Tom had vowed to never let bad habits take root, to be disciplined and vigilant at all times. The most successful attack is one that comes when you aren't expecting it. Tom opened the door with his left hand while the right hung low ready to be armed with his wand with another flick of the wrist. He already had a rather nasty curse in mind: a quick upward slash of his wand to tear through almost any ward and every bit of flesh which it would be protecting, spattering the castle's ancient walls with a mist...

As he opened the door, he saw a rather large seventh year standing menacingly before him. At least, the young man's posture and body language obviously meant to project danger and evoke fear to the average person. Tom almost smiled - he hadn't even bothered to properly evaluate this student on his "danger scale". In fact, he couldn't even recall the boy's name now that he thought of it. The only thing that seemed weaker than this boy's knowledge of casting was the force behind those spells. Still, all his obvious incompetence could have been a bluff leading up to this moment... an unlikely attack with overwhelming magic. Tom refused to let himself be fooled; he pushed that nifty little cutting curse on the top of his mind.

In a flash the youth's demeanour changed. Tom hadn't said a word or made a gesture in the few moments they had been facing each other, but it was obvious the other student felt the raw magic pulsating as they stood there. His magic did that sometimes when he was annoyed or angry, he normally rather liked that effect, despite knowing he eventually had to master it. Using your raw magic like that was supposed to be very advanced, so Tom tended to take it as a good sign when it just happened on its own. The person on the receiving end of this growing feeling of cold relentless magic filling the air never seemed to appreciate the delicacy of it as much as Tom did, alas.

"I'm sorry to bother you so late, Riddle." The youth was looking rather tired suddenly.

"Professor Dumbledore has asked me to tell you to come to his office immediately. He stressed to me that this was important. He didn't seem to be in a good mood…" The boy finished his sentence as if he was speaking to his shoes.

"Thank you." Tom waved his hand and dismissed the messenger who was apparently glad to go.

Tom left his room and walked through the common room towards the exit. A few students yet milled about, studying or talking about mundane things. Tom noticed MacNair sitting at a table, his head was down on the wooden table top, and his wand was a foot in front of his face. He stared at the wooden rod, apparently lost in thought.

Tom hated to be interrupted when he was thinking deeply; he had no compunctions whatsoever about interrupting somebody else, however. "You can't empower your wand with your own magic MacNair, trust me, I've tried." He said it sarcastically, but a clever person would take it as a joke rather than an insult, and MacNair was clever. Just how clever the buy was even Tom couldn't say.

MacNair lifted his head, sunken cheeks dominating his face, looked up at Tom as if to speak, but he hesitated.

Tom tried to look friendly, for he had no ill feelings towards MacNair. Quite the contrary, Tom considered him to be one of the least useless students attending this school. Recently he had even considered asking the boy to join his Battle Magic "lessons". For the last year it had simply been Tom and Chang, fighting wand to wand and fist to fist on the edge of the Forbidden Forest near the mountains. Chang was a hard fighter, but Tom could always overwhelm him if he needed to. He needed more opponents, more students...

MacNair was hesitating to speak; Tom's reputation always made people consider before they spoke to him, even his "friends", so he had to encourage the boy with the sunken cheeks to open up.

"What's so interesting about your wand?" Tom asked as he sat down to observe the light brown stick for himself. Perhaps MacNair had some type of thought Tom might be interested in.

MacNair took a moment to figure out how to speak his thoughts.

"Well, I mean, think about it, Tom," he said, snatching the wand and holding it up in front of his own face.

"The magical core that generates a wand's power is generally made from creatures people consider good." MacNair spun his wand around his fingers, back and forth, so precise and quickly it impressed even Tom. "Unicorns, Phoenixes, Veela. The most dangerous creature that I know they use to make wands from is dragons."

MacNair paused, obviously lost in thought. Speaking almost more to himself then to Tom, the boy continued.

"My wand has a dragon heartstring in it. I have to say I've certainly noticed that when I cast fire spells, or more destructive spells, they are much more potent than I would have expected given my own natural ability."

MacNair was on a roll. "What if a person made a wand from say, a hair from a troll?" He paused to consider his own question. "Would their spell casting have more brute strength? Would they be able to adapt to transfiguration more easily?"

Tom couldn't answer these questions; he was ashamed to admit to himself that he had never even considered these things.

MacNair continued, "What if you used, say a piece of a Dementors cloak as your wand core?"

Tom shuddered involuntarily; he took a second to regain his composure before he spoke. "I expect the wand would have some interesting properties."

That much was true, who knows what powers you could wield with the magic of a Dementor?

Tom continued, "However, I would never touch such a wand myself. I also expect that it would degrade and fall to bits within weeks of its creation, no matter how well it was crafted."

Tom felt truly interested in this conversation. MacNair might be onto something with his talk of wands. Tom had never considered looking into wandlore, a terrible oversight in retrospect; there could be powerful secrets there. The problem was there were powerful secrets in every ignored aspect of magic.

MacNair looked at Tom and frowned. "A Dementor was a poor example, I admit."

Very poor, but the thought was interesting.

MacNair went on after a moment. "I mean, I know David Monroe has much more magical power then I do, yet my fire spells burn twice as hot as his do." The boy was gaining confidence as he spoke. "Monroe uses a wand with a unicorn hair core, and I've noticed that his spellcasting is quicker and more graceful than you would expect, even given his talent."

Tom glanced over to the corner of the common room where Monroe was sitting in a large chair with a blonde in his lap. He whispered something to her that made her laugh. Tom couldn't help frowning. David Monroe had far too much unjustified confidence in himself. If the boy's bravado started to peak again, Tom would be forced to humble Monroe once more.

MacNair's voice cut into Tom's thoughts. "Do you think that a wizard's magic is more focused and powerful in areas their wands are comfortable in?" He was looking to Tom as though he was asking a question to a professor in class.

Tom considered it for a moment; he had to give MacNair some credit, he might be onto something.

"Your idea certainly seems to make sense, I must admit. However, I think that it will be much more complicated than it may seem on the surface. I suggest you start asking around, find out what type of wands everyone uses. From there try to analyze the types of magic they excel in - there may well be a connection."

Tom paused and tapped his cheek with his finger before he continued. "There are actually a good number of books which mention wandlore in the library. If I were you, I would read those as well." Tom planned to read those books himself at some point now that MacNair had made such an interesting observation.

Surely I can find some secret to use to my advantage.

Tom held up his own wand. Phoenix feather. Those birds were supposed to be one of the most powerful creatures on earth. Tom had started mastering wandless magic before he even knew he was a wizard, but once he had a wand he certainly became much more powerful. The core of his wand may help explain his extraordinarily powerful spells, natural skill aside. Phoenixes come back from death as well.

MacNair hung on Tom's every word. "I kind have been doing that already. You know, finding out who uses what wand, but you're right. I need to get more examples before I can really say for sure. Some of those books would help too; I'll have to visit the library."

Tom was glad he had stopped to chat with MacNair. Not only did he get a new mystery to think about, but Tom's opinion of the boy intelligence solidified once he heard of the boy's theory and saw his desire to look deeper.

Still, it was time to go. "Dumbledore has summoned me for some sort of chastisement, I have to assume. I'm afraid we'll have to continue this later."

The other boy's face was frozen. "Ok Tom, good luck with that old meddler. I hope he goes easy on you."

Tom doubted he needed luck, and he was slightly annoyed, why would the boy care one way or the other? Try not to be so transparent, please...

As Tom made his way down the hallway he allowed himself to wonder what this summoning could regard. It was too near the beginning of fifth year for any plot against his fellow students. All the plots from last year were either dead or too well established to be uncovered. Tom guessed he had done more than a few things Dumbledore would disapprove of over the summer, but none of those could possibly have been found out, even by the old meddler.

Tom entered the Transfiguration classroom and walked toward the thick door at the back of the room.

He knocked, a pointless gesture with Dumbledore's wards alerting him to Tom's presence. Oddly enough, Dumbledore was normally at the door and opening it as you reached up to bang on the wood, but not even the knock brought him forth. Obviously some type of game going on here. Tom never had to wait to be scolded or praised, whichever the case may be. So clearly this was some new tactic of Dumbledore's. Whatever the old man hoped to accomplish by making Tom wait would fail this time; Tom would be patient and sit here all night. If Tom could actually think of a reason Dumbledore would be especially angry, he may try to start off timid. As far as he could see though there was no reason for that, so Tom would act boldly.

There was no reason for him to stand at attention like a student to be scolded, waiting on Dumbledore while his own legs got tired. He almost took a step toward a desk before he stopped and sneered. I'm a wizard, not a Muggle, I'd best remember it. With a wave of his wand, two of the desks slid across the floor and stopped in front of him. He touched the first desk with his wand and focused on a complex Transfiguration. Within moments, the desk was a tall throne almost touching the high ceiling, from which he could look down on the old wizard once he deigned to appear. He admired it for a moment, and then touched his wand to create stairs on the bottom of the throne. This was a new technique Tom had been working on; it took three whole minutes before the Transfiguration of the stairs held. Tom climbed the stairs proudly, glad that the combination of a transfiguration and an illusion enchantment succeeded.

Tom next transfigured the other desk into a large very dramatic looking hourglass, which was much easier work. If you want to play a game, I'll certainly play with you. How long the wait ended up could help determine how angry the man was. Really, most of the time Tom got away with his "schemes" as Dumbledore called them, by playing the innocent and misunderstood student, or setting up somebody else to take the blame. If Dumbledore was already trying to send messages, this would have to be a different type of conversation than their usual cryptic yet apparently friendly ones.

Tom also considered that this might be nothing bad at all. Dumbledore could be too strange to predict, it was even possible Tom was here to be praised for something, but he doubted it. Why make him wait in that case? No, this seemed like a "stern lecture". He would know when he saw the man, if it was some trivial matter the old meddler would likely be briefly impressed at the detail in Tom's Transfigurations, and then proceed to laugh off the subtle messages and instead focus on the new technique Tom had just used to weave the stairs into a flowing, yet steady stream of black iron. Tom specifically crafted it especially to grab the man's attention. Normally nothing pleased him, but hopefully it would change their first interaction from a negative to a positive right from the start as well. Why not play on the man's interests.

Transfiguration was one of the old man's passions, and as it happened; Tom was also very interested in this subject himself. It was unbelievably useful, and Tom had made a point to excel with this particular magic. A love of learning was something Tom had in common with the old man. Many times Tom had come to this office, to ask about a certain fundamental principle of a certain magic, or run a new theory past him and learn from the ancient wizard. Dumbledore would actually sit with him and appear to consider Tom's ideas as though they came from an equal. Tom tried to use these personal lessons to build the man's trust and slowly learn his potent magics. Any secrets he could squeeze out of the wise old man would be beneficial, though he had learned nothing of any true potency from Dumbledore. Even his most subtle and humble attempts came to nothing.

More importantly, Tom was trying to build trust so he could earn a place among the staff one day. It was working, though not nearly as well as Tom had thought it would. There was no denying that the man had some level of trust and respect for Tom, at least when it came to his competence in Transfiguration, but that wouldn't be enough. The old wizard had to be in awe at Tom's skill on some level, or he wouldn't have allowed him to learn of the existence of Dumbledore's "Top Secret High Magic Transfiguration Laboratory". Tom was actually allowed inside to learn from the man and try his own experiments on a few occasions. Other professors had told him that he was the first student to even know of that room's existence. However, Tom hadn't been asked to join the man in his private room in quite some time.

Really, Tom Riddle did not like Albus Dumbledore. The man had a strange way of thinking that Tom couldn't agree with. He did however respect him as a powerful and competent wizard. Not to mention, Tom not being stupid, he also had a healthy level of fear of a man capable of wielding the types and level of magic Dumbledore could.

Dumbledore taught Transfiguration classes and Tom had to admit that as far as professors went, Dumbledore was excellent. His Transfiguration classes were actually entertaining and even insightful on occasion. Unlike most of the other professors, Dumbledore wouldn't frown on him trying to disprove something from the book. Nor would the old man try to limit Tom to the standard curriculum. If he was quite capable of the day's lesson, he was free to try a more advanced procedure and go practice in the corner. Dumbledore would even come over to give him advice from time to time. Tom absolutely disliked the old man, but couldn't deny that he respected him. He felt that Dumbledore held Tom in a similar regard.

Dumbledore would never dare try to hinder somebody's potential and could only respect the ambition and aptitude he showed at his age. But Dumbledore is always suspicious of him, always assuming the worst. The man was usually right, to be fair; Tom did get into some shady business, but Dumbledore shouldn't be able to see though the humble student facade Tom put on. Because of this, Tom still wasn't fully sure of the dynamics of this relationship. The old man once spent so much time trying to "advise" Tom. Perhaps it was because he truly respected the potential and wanted to be his mentor. That would explain why he wanted to try to take Tom off of the "dark path" he had once said Tom was apparently on. He had tried, but Tom didn't much care what anyone considered "dark." There were too many "dark" spells which were utterly useful in regular situations, Tom knew.

Another consideration was that the man may have a better insight into Tom's real thoughts and ideas than he had ever suspected. In that case, the "Friendly lessons and chats" would be Dumbledore's way of keeping an eye on Tom or even trying to keep him in check. Tom was unsure - probably a little of both of those options, probably a third Tom would never understand. Dumbledore was a man who was very hard to read.

The door to the back office opened finally and the old man was standing there. He had a disappointed frown on his face - he was clearly annoyed, and Tom was about to receive a stern talking-to for some reason. Dumbledore's slight anger pushed his natural magic to take shape and radiate off the man, giving the atmosphere a hot tingling feeling. Most children would be cowering at this building pressure in the room, but Tom knew it merely meant Dumbledore was a powerful wizard, no news there.

Tom had learned you had to do something truly terrible to make Dumbledore truly angry. He had never seen the legendary "Angry Albus Dumbledore" but he had heard of the intensity of it. Tom could believe it was a sight to behold. If Dumbledore projects this much power when he's displeased, the magic must be absolutely tangible when the man gets furious. Tom imagined Dumbledore could easily walk through most wards as if they were air in the right situation, if he could radiate that much raw magic.

With a quick gesture from Dumbledore's wand, Tom's transfigurations were undone, and he felt himself floated gently down to the ground in order to prevent the five-foot fall. Tom hated that. So condescending; does he think me a child incapable of catching myself with my own magic?

That was a message too as far as he could tell. Normally, Dumbledore at least started off amiable and friendly in their talks even if he suspected Tom of some "mischief". Normally it would first, be a lame attempt at humor and light chitchat, while Dumbledore tried to feel him out. This time the Professor seemed more than merely annoyed with Tom, and he was going to get straight to the point, whatever that may be. I really can't imagine what he thinks I've done, why is he acting so differently this time? As Tom was being led into the inner office, he thought frantically about which plots could possibly be discovered.

Suddenly Tom realized what this could be about. It had been at least a week since he had last made the house elves confess if they had betrayed him or not. That laziness might have cost him something here; Tom supposed he would find out.

Dumbledore's personal office was a place of great power even within this ancient magic castle. The large oak door alone would intimidate to a lesser person. It radiated power; Tom could easily detect some four to six wards around the office on any given day, and feel the edges of dozens more, so it was safe to say there were many more he couldn't even begin to comprehend. Tom was quite sure he would be unable to break through that door if he had to, even using the most potent magic currently available to him would probably not even scratch the wood. The door slammed behind him as he walked into the office itself, the lock clicked loudly despite there being no actual lock or knob for that matter. Tom made it across the room and to his chair first. He tried to sit down but there was an invisible barrier around the chair and he couldn't touch it; his hand was stopped dead by an invisible wall as he made to grab the back of the chair.

Dumbledore was across the room in a few long strides and took a seat in his own chair. Only after Dumbledore was seated did Tom feel the ward on the chair dissipate. The man wasn't even trying to be subtle; Tom disliked this sudden change in attitude, it was unexpected and probably unnecessary. As Tom sat he noticed the old man had his wand sitting out on the desk. It was not pointing directly at Tom but in his general direction, inches from the powerful wizard's grasp. There could be another message there - but knowing Dumbledore it could be anything. "If you can snatch it and overtake me, I will not oppose you." Perhaps, but that really did not seem likely. And of course there could be no message there at all; it could be that's just where the man keeps it while sitting, easy enough to summon to hand instantly. After four full years as a Slytherin, Tom instantly tended to try and find the hidden meaning in every action a person made in his presence, but with Dumbledore he usually failed.

Dumbledore looked at him, his normally twinkling eyes now piercing blue ice. Tom knew full well what that meant, and he simply couldn't allow it. He had taken measures to learn how to protect his mind, in addition to how to get past other people's barriers and search their thoughts.

Dumbledore must have picked up on Tom's Occlumency training at some point however. Tom had thought he had been extraordinarily subtle about it, Dumbledore must be good. Tom hadn't wanted the man to know that he was on his way to becoming a perfect Occlumens. He had planned to use Dumbledore's own legilimency against him. Tom would have fed him an innocent but misunderstood Tom Riddle, a Tom Riddle whose actions are filled with good intentions regardless of the results. It was one of the ways he planned to gain the man's trust. But Tom must have overestimated his own ability and given the game away. Those blue eyes no longer tried to pierce Tom's mind. Dumbledore must now know Tom was hiding his true thoughts from him and decided to not bother trying any longer. If Dumbledore had really discovered Tom's barriers there was a certain trust that would always be broken.

"Tell me, Mister Riddle," Dumbledore said with no hint of his normal cheer, "what exactly have you done to the house elves?"

Tom had decided to adapt his answers to Dumbledore's reactions rather than go in with a set story. He'd put an innocent and ignorant face on, then replied, "Why, nothing sir. Nothing really, I've had them tend to a few extra tasks but that is what they live for sir. I've become friends with the elf which tends to my room, and he almost insisted on helping me more."

Dumbledore was not moved. "I know it goes further than that, Mister Riddle. You have somehow hoodwinked them all into your service." Dumbledore was growing sterner by the moment. "I'll have you know that I personally consider the elves to be esteemed Hogwarts staff as much as myself. I do not take kindly to students playing games with them for their own amusement."

Dumbledore paused for a moment. "Even the Headmaster himself was distressed to learn of the abuse the house elves were suffering."

Dumbledore was starting to lose steam. "The Headmaster may not feel as strongly about it as I do."

Dumbledore looked annoyed at that, but continued with a new found passion. "I will certainly see to it that he takes it as seriously as it should be taken though."

Dumbledore was looking at Tom now with a hint of disgust on his face. "I do not understand your true purpose for rallying the elves under your control." Dumbledore looked at Tom with his head tilted sideways in confusion and paused before continuing.

"Mister Riddle, the complexity of your plots is getting to the point that I can leave no loopholes for you. Perhaps this is all a mistake on my part, but it seems it could possibly be something much greater which requires my attention."

Tom took that as a compliment and a challenge, though he hid his smile behind his mask.

"There will be an announcement to the school soon." Dumbledore said it firmly and let it hang before going on. "As much as it pains me, I will be personally seeing to it that the entire house elf management system is redesigned."

Tom was curious about this; he could surely find a way around a redesign if he wanted to. Dumbledore was looking far less enthusiastic than he had been before when he spoke again.

"These changes will hurt people Tom. You say you have made friends with your elf, well others have as well and they will be hurt."

Dumbledore looked at Tom hard. Tom did his best to pretend that meant something.

"Mister Riddle, you may not have any affection for lesser beings, no matter what you claim, but other students do. Friendships will die because of whatever plot you were working on, that is a sad thing, Tom."

Dumbledore looked like he meant it, though Tom didn't see how that was sad in that context. It was certainly a shame his plot had been foiled so early, that was slightly sad.

Tom spent many late nights in his private dorm, a privilege only granted to him because he stayed at Hogwarts all year and it just made sense for a top student living at school to have their own quarters. He stayed up late reading books or practicing spells when most of the castle slept. As a result of his study he had become "friendly" with the house elf that goes by the name "Truuey."

Truuey was assigned to Tom's personal chamber. He was to keep it fresh and clean, and see to any small needs Tom may have. Tom asked who had assigned him to his particular room and the elf told him nobody assigned anything. The elves just knew what needed to be done and came to mutual agreements on the assigning of tasks.

From there Tom had reasoned with the elf that since he was a Hogwarts servant bound particularly to Tom's service it only made sense if the elf followed his explicit orders. It didn't take much convincing; the house elves weren't very intelligent creatures. Once Tom had sold that idea to the elf, he also reasoned with the creature that things would be more efficiently run if there was a "Head House Elf". An elf that delegated responsibilities and punishments to all the other elves, if it could be done in an intelligent and organized way it would only help the castle run better. Tom compared it to the way wizards do things although he disagreed wizards ran anything properly, and the elf seemed to like the idea after a little coaxing and manipulating.

It only took a few days, and a few motivational speeches and tips for controlling underlings until Truuey was more or less the dictator that all the other house elves followed with absolute loyalty. House elves were surprisingly agreeable even given their reputation. It only took a week and a half for them to accept and adapt to a global change in an 800 year old system. That was impressive even by Tom's ridiculously high standards. He had known the whole setup was first configured by none other than Helga Hufflepuff and it had probably never changed since implemented. He had foolishly assumed she couldn't be as dim as the stories made her seem but all his experience in the castle had made it obvious that the founders should have reviewed her ideas before they engraved them into the castles system. Surely Dumbledore would change things in time when he came into power, but for now it was almost too easy for Tom to game the systems.

Tom had taken time to build his relationship with the elf which served him, and once Truuey was absolutely loyal to Tom he basically had total control of the entire Hogwarts house elf faction. Their strange magical constrictions made it easy for Tom to program in a near unbeatable system of silence. It could still be beaten, but only by the headmaster. The elves bound to Hogwarts had to answer to the Headmaster above all, regardless of other vows or constrictions. Tom had found that you could trick them into sorts of vows of silence however. Only if asked specific questions by the Headmaster could the elf answer those questions, and even then they had to use very specific answers providing no extra detail. House elf magic was rather odd and specific, useful as well.

So far Tom had only been giving commands that would cause general confusion and disorder on a small scale, to further particular plots. Sometimes he would just generally use the elves' covert skills to harass the people he disliked. Last week Tom had the elves remove the bedding from three different people's beds and replace it with the itchy type no one could be comfortable in. Building a team of minions inside the castle took time, he had to start small and go unnoticed. Apparently I've failed at going unnoticed.

Dumbledore broke him out of thought, "Tom, I demand you stop any and all interaction with the house elves from here on out. This is not negotiable. If you have a certain need my door is always open to you, and I can help you with nearly anything. You are, under no circumstances, to issue orders of any type to any of the elves. You shall not direct other students to manipulate the elves either, nor shall you twist my words in any way to find a hole you can slip through. Have I made myself clear on this matter?" Dumbledore stared at him for a long moment.

"Yes sir." Tom forced out, very annoyed about this. There was a great deal of power to be had in the school if you could wield the house elves cleverly. Surely he could find a way around whatever restrictions Dumbledore forced Headmaster Dippet to put into effect... but there were more important things to focus on. The elves were an acceptable loss by Tom's standards.

"I understand Professor, it was probably wrong of me to ask them to take on even more work on top of everything else they have to do." Tom paused to look down at the desk as though he was ashamed, as he had seen others do.

He then looked up and continued with the shame gone from his face and an indignant stare took its place. Tom made sure to put force into his words when he spoke. "I simply had them doing things like fetching materials for experiments or sending messages to people in my study groups. Perhaps have them bringing me food at odd hours while I study. That type of thing. That is what they are in the school for Professor, is it not? They haven't complained to me at all."

Dumbledore's face was impossible to read as he spoke. "That is more or less their job Tom; however they are not any student's slave. They would not complain if you asked them to break stones using muggle hammers all day either, it's their nature."

Tom tried to look taken aback at the word, "Slave sir? Tuuey was my friend." Tom looked away from Dumbledore, toward one of the odd objects on the shelf as he let the comment sink in.

Dumbledore looked halfway satisfied with that answer; Tom had put enough "emotion" behind the word friend to cause a brief flash of doubt cross through the old wizard's eyes. However Tom wasn't convinced this was the end of matter.

"You may go then Tom, it is getting late." The powerful door behind him clicked again and swung open. Apparently it was the end of it, at least the end of the conversation. Dumbledore would work tirelessly against this plot from every angle after this.

However if that was all Dumbledore had to say on the matter, then Tom was fairly sure his complex set of commands and vows had prevented the old man from learning anything other than his involvement in using extra house elves to help him. Tom was also sure Headmaster Dippet wouldn't have pressed the issue too hard when questioning them for Dumbledore.

Tom got up and started to walk out and as he did he heard Professor Dumbledore speak from behind him in a softer voice.

"I did like the extra detail you put into the stairs on your throne by the way. It looked very complicated, and extremely comfortable."

Tom looked back and the man had regained just a little of his regular cheeriness. Tom simply nodded at him and walked out as a scolded student should.

As he headed back to his dorm he reflected on the loss. An army of unseen minions running around the school at night doing his bidding was certainly a huge loss. He could have slowly over the years used the elves as one of many factors in completely taking over the school. As far as he understood once the elves developed a deep enough pattern of following his specific orders as a "master" they would be bond to him nearly as much as the Headmaster.

There would be pretty much nothing they wouldn't have done in my service if I could trick them into thinking they were accomplishing something else, once the situation got to that point. What did I fail to consider? I missed something if it went wrong so quickly.

Tom wasn't used to a thought-out plan coming undone so quickly and spectacularly. He had taken care to use specific words and phrases while talking to Tuuey, and the elf would have repeated him exactly to the underlings which were similarly bound. It would have taken a very specific line of questioning from the lazy headmaster himself for them to reveal they were taking orders from Tom.

Tom thought about Dumbledore's involvement. He knew that Dumbledore not only spoke with the Merfolk and Centaurs, but took pleasure in it. The old man had to translate for the Headmaster if there were ever problems in the lake or forest. Tom had naturally assumed Dumbledore would speak with the cleaning and cooking "staff" as well but there was no reason the old meddler should have started pressing the Headmaster to ask the right questions. Questions like, "Did Tom Riddle take you into his service, Tuuey?" Or perhaps, "Did Tom Riddle ask you to take over the kitchen, Tuuey?" A very specific line of questioning would be the only way to confirm anything Tom had done with them.

Thinking it over, in retrospect the reformation was rather fast. Tom should have played it out for a year or two before taking total control. He should have used few extra elves now, a few more to his service a few months later and so on. That would have probably gone unseen. Tom had been overambitious and started wielding his elves far too hard too soon. It must have been obvious enough to take note of a plot if somebody was paying attention. Tom hadn't even thought that anybody would glance in that direction; since they were just elves doing what appeared to be work. Dumbledore's bizarre empathy towards the creatures might have been his undoing here; he hadn't considered that at all. Sure Dumbledore might speak with a few from time to time, but that couldn't reveal any plot.

The house elves were acting generally the same as they usually do. They were always cheery and ready for work. Perhaps some were a little tired and overworked, but Tom would never take one out of regular rotation and disrupt regular tasks, which could be noticed by somebody. Tom would use the ones who were currently allotted their required resting time when he needed them, so as to not attract attention. Tom would never have considered somebody would actually take notice of the lowly creatures. Who would have noticed the subtle decrease in their well-being? Ridiculous, they're elves. They had their uses but they didn't warrant that type of compassion. Tom had to wonder how exactly the mind of Albus Dumbledore worked if he could relate to an elf.

Chapter 6: Tom Riddle and Misunderstandings

Chapter Six – Tom Riddle and Misunderstandings

Tom Riddle sat in the Headmaster's office alone. The headmaster and Dumbledore had brought him in and left him to stew while they - tried to investigate - Tom assumed.

He was casually drawing patterns of smoke in the air with his fingers as he waited for Dippet and Dumbledore to return with whatever ideas they had.

He had been pleased that he had some time alone before the interrogation; he needed time to regain his composure after his transformation, and also to puzzle out just what Black had gotten him into - and how he could get out of it.

This is getting ridiculous. Surely they don't think they'll find anything after an hour? Waste of everybody's time, especially mine...

Tom leaned back, drew a jagged seven-pointed star in the air and admired it for a few moments. It began to change color, from a grey mist into a fiery rune, a flaming crimson light. Tom watched it grow in intensity for a few moments, then, dismissing it with a wave of his hand, he leaned back in the chair to think.

"Well, what do you think, Albus?" Headmaster Dippet asked as the man returned from the dorm.

Albus Dumbledore frowned. "I didn't see anything overly suspicious, his wand hasn't done anything of note recently, and his room does not seem to have any lingering magic that is of major concern." He didn't want to mention the intensity of lingering Transfiguration, since Dippet was hardly the expert, but it had seemed almost unfamiliar at first.

Albus went on. "I believe on this matter it may come down to a misunderstanding. Even I find these particular claims a little too far-fetched. However, we will still need to speak with Mr. Riddle about it, and while we have the chance, we should talk to him regarding the other matter. The two may be related in some way I cannot see yet." At any rate, he was deeply curious to hear Tom's excuses and his version of events.

Headmaster Dippet frowned. "Oh Albus! Do you really think Tom is involved with this other nonsense? Still? It hardly seems like a matter worth investigating In my own opinion."

Albus did not, but if Tom Riddle was in fact involved, it was a cause for deep concern. "It's worth looking into in any case while we have him here," he replied shortly. After all, how many innocent misunderstandings with one boy could there be? Eventually you start had to connecting the dots, even if the patterns were abstract and made little sense.

Albus Dumbledore had taken it upon himself to try to tame the wildness in the boy over the years. There was much potential in him, yes. However, it had seemed like a lost cause from the start, and perhaps Albus hadn't tried as hard as he could have. But when you took a boy who had such control over his magic before even taking a wand, and left him so long among Muggles, how could his stubbornness and independence be a surprise?

"Albus, what's wrong?" Headmaster Dippet crinkled his eyes, tipped his head to the right, and stepped closer to him.

Albus Dumbledore shook his head to disregard the question, and put on a passive expression. "Let us go to speak with Mr. Riddle, and get to the bottom of this, shall we?"

Finally, finally, Tom heard footsteps. He had been waiting in silence so long that he started, fearing for an instant that Aurors were coming to arrest him, before his natural calm reasserted itself. The Headmaster, coming to apologize. And -ha! - Dumbledore.

It had been long enough that Tom's mind had started to wander and look at his situation from every angle. He had been careful, but one could always be more careful. Underestimating Albus Dumbledore would be a mistake he shouldn't make again - he hardly counted the House Elves - but it would be just like the old man to put together a pattern to deduce Tom's extra-curricular activities. And if so... then this was all a ruse to get him alone and unarmed.

Tom had absolutely no intentions of ever being captured willingly. Even if he didn't seriously think he was on the verge of being arrested at this point, it was something to consider.

"Your plan has to have at least 3 backups or it was like to fail".

He sat in his chair with his fingers interlocked behind his head; he was facing the desk and rear wall, with his back to the door. He was admiring the brightness of the blue sky outside the window a few feet behind the desk. If three Aurors were coming to get him, there was no point in facing the door without a wand. As far as Tom could see, his best bet was to play dumb and timid until the last possible moment.

Unless Dumbledore is present… He may be invisible, so assume he is present to oversee the arrest… Dumbledore would see through a false surrender. Then I suppose I'd have to at least argue and make threats…

You couldn't feel magic outside the Headmaster's office with the door closed - at any rate, Tom couldn't. And a silencing spell would quiet all traces of noise. All he could do was wait; once the door opened, he would be able to feel the presence of an Auror trio without having to look.

Tom was trying to focus his magic and build it up as much as he could, in case he needed to spring to action.

"Merlin!" Tom whispered.

Not only had his magic returned to him at an impressive rate, but the well of his power was much deeper than before he had completed the transformation. He had expected some sort of boost, but the increase was shocking even by his standards. He found that he had to suppress his magic now, as to not cause immediate alarm if the authorities came in. Whether Aurors or simply the Headmaster, he would have to explain even more if they felt him holding so much magic.

It was dawning on Tom that "Unforgiveable Curses" were in fact punishable by a life sentence in Azkaban. And despite his youth, arson, robbery and extortion would probably be more than a slap on the wrist. Not to mention the other things Tom had to do sometimes to earn money, or "pay" Tobo Mott.

I have been careful though… They might suspect things, but they can't PROVE anything. They can't prove anything, unless Dumbledore put some arcane magical trace on me. Some radical magic which I know nothing of and Tobo cannot sense… And that is highly unlikely.

Tom shook his head at that notion, and at how ridiculous the law was. It was probable that they didn't even require any real proof against him, only circumstantial evidence of a "true crime", of which he had committed plenty. Then they would give him a "trial," which would be little more than a formality, before he was shipped off to the… The Dementors...

No, no! The Headmaster is just searching, and since there is nothing to find, they are taking a while. That's all.

He would be prepared for anything however.

If it is a capture mission, they would likely only use the standard trio for an unarmed 5thyear student… The Aurors would come in single file, immediately to spread out and surround me in a triangle the moment they walked in, shields and wands raised.

Tom smiled and leaned back even further in his chair.

If they surrounded him where he sat in front of the desk, then one of them would have to go around the desk to form the capture triangle for the arrest. That Auror would then come back around, breaking formation once Tom was on his feet and walking towards the door.

They won't expect anything at all from a wandless fifth year student.

Tom smiled; he was beginning to almost hope they were coming to arrest him, it could prove interesting. He could see it now: he would stand up, raise his hands in surrender, then turn to the door as if to leave peacefully, frightened and helpless, in total submission. But the moment his back would turn to the window, the triangle broken, he would simply stumble back a step and bring his hands down. A massive blast cast to reflect off of the Auror's shields could propel him backwards through the window.

Tom stared at the window and felt the edges of the wards. One enormous burst of his entire magical load as he was flying towards the window should be able to pierce the wards - Dippet's office was nowhere nearly as heavily warded as Dumbledore's, so it wouldn't require anything else.

Tom would have walked over to the window to calculate the drop, but he couldn't be sure they weren't magically watching him right this moment. So he simply estimated how high he was in the castle at the moment. About two hundred feet, but he could time another blast/shield output to offset the impact. And once he was on the ground, the Whomping Willow was but a short sprint away. Especially with an adrenaline burst.

Running the distance before an auror got a shot off out the window and hit him would be the most difficult part as far as Tom could tell. If they had any type of real training they were probably at least as good a shot as he was, and the window was large.

Tom didn't think anything he had done was enough to justify burning through the wall with Fiendfyre and coming after him, but that would be one thing he couldn't fight against. On the other hand, Aurors probably wouldn't do that at Hogwarts but for a very last resort, which would mean he was absolutely done for. Highly unlikely, at any rate, so all he'd have to do was run fast, and he was a very fast runner. Outrun the shots, press the hidden knot, go into the secret passage, grab his hidden emergency luggage, and he could then be easily out of the country by midnight.

The biggest unknown would be the ministry's reaction time, but it really didn't matter too much. After all, once he had past the Hogwarts' wards, he could apparate anywhere.

Tom could make it that far down the serpentine passageway in 25 seconds flat under the effects of the road runner potion in his bag, though it would cost him energy once it wore off. Polyjuiced and dressed as an old muggle woman should give him sufficient safe recovery time once he was away however.

It's a shame to leave my true wand behind, but –

Tom's thoughts were cut off by the noise of footsteps. Two people walking. Two old people walking. Dippet and Dumbledore.

Hm. It's almost a shame.

"Headmaster, I'd ask that you explain why I have been detained." Tom still faced the window.

"I'm sorry, Mister Riddle. You see, there had been a number of, err, strange rumors, and we had to be sure of some things." The Headmaster was coming around to sit at his desk now while Dumbledore took a seat on the side, observing Tom intently the entire time.

"May I have my wand back, please, sir?"

Tom had asked Dippet, but it was Dumbledore who handed it over almost grudgingly.

Oh, so very reluctant to arm me again!

Tom gave it a wave to see if it had been tampered with, but it felt utterly perfect on first glance. I'll have to do some more vigorous testing on it later.

Tom looked up at Dippet, and then to Dumbledore. "What was the nature of these 'rumors', sirs?" Tom asked.

Dippet replied, "Well Mister Riddle, Terence Keen had said Bellatrix Black admitted the two of you were performing some sort of dark ritual."

Apparently saying I was in the library was too complicated for her.

Dippet continued, "Also, another student reported that he saw you take a cage into your room shortly before, apparently containing a number of squirrels."

"Excuse me sir, which student would that be?" Tom demanded.

Dumbledore was the one to answer him, "That does not matter, Mister Riddle. It is clear to me that no ritual was performed, and I myself see no benefit of using squirrels to any end."

And we see Dumbledore's lack of creativity has saved me.

Dumbledore was leaning forward now and staring at Tom with his blue eyes now stormy. "However Mister Riddle, I am curious about the Transfigurations you were performing in your room."

Tom smiled at Dumbledore. "Why, sir, I was just preparing for my OWLs, nothing too fancy, but I was certainly practicing hard." Tom sighed deeply. "That is why I asked Miss Black to send anyone looking for me on a goose chase to the library." He then forcefully said, "I didn't want to be interrupted while I studied." In a calmer voice, he went on, "Why Miss Black started making such inappropriate jokes I couldn't say, but, believe me, sir, there was nothing special happening this afternoon."

Tom was putting on his very best innocent-orphan-act, but Dumbledore's eyes remained fierce as he spoke. "Mister Riddle, I fully expected you to pass your Transfiguration OWL with flying colors as early as two years ago. I have never known you to be the type to take tests so seriously."

Tom was starting to become confused. What did I say?

"Well Sir, I see now that these tests are serious, and I mean to do well." Tom shrugged his shoulders.

"Upon inspecting your wand, the last spells you cast were seemingly for target practice, having nothing to do with Transfiguration," Dumbledore pointed out.

Obviously, I wasn't using my wand, old fool!

"I was taking a short break, leisure time," Tom replied.

"Why was your basic Transfiguration so important that Miss Black must prevent anybody from interrupting you?" Dumbledore was on him again, faster and more intent.

Calm as ever, Tom replied, "It wasn't important, sir, I would wager that Miss Black probably read into what I was saying and projected her own silly ideas. Poor girl." He tried to put an air of a long-suffering suitor with an undesired suit. "Besides, sir, my Transfiguration ought not to be called 'basic', I think you would have to agree with me on that point, Professor." Tom smiled broadly.

The instant Tom was quiet, Dumbledore asked another question, with no hint of appreciation for the wit. "Why are you scaring children during the night, Mr. Riddle?" Dumbledore was leaning forward even more now, and Tom could feel magic pressure building.

Tom was speechless. "I… What, excuse me sir could you elaborate on that last one?" Apparently something was going on that Tom Riddle was actually not responsible for. But his memory did seem to recall such an incident, despite it not seeming relevant enough to fully impress upon him.

Dumbledore paused for a moment and seemed to almost relax, but when he spoke his voice was still as sharp and focused as before. "Children have been roaming around at night, trying to sneak into the kitchens. The House Elves don't deliver late night snacks to them anymore as they once would on occasion."

Tom bit his lip to stop from smiling as Dumbledore continued.

"During their roaming, they have been chased off several times by what they describe as terrifying noises." He stared at Tom. "So you see, I thought perhaps you were behind this, since you were involved with the Elves in the first place. Not to mention your history of 'mischievous' behaviour around the school." Dumbledore was looking at him with absolutely no expression now, which Tom found even more disconcerting than the open hostility.

"I see…" And for once, Tom was totally honest as he spoke to Dippet. "Well, I assure the both of you, I am no way concerned with scaring children in the night; I have far better things to do. I do recall hearing a snippet of conversation about these events at one point, but other than that, I am at as much of a loss as you as to what is happening. I don't know what else I can say on that matter, Sirs."

It's almost relaxing to be so honest.

Dumbledore nodded and leaned back, "I believe you then, Tom."

Tom simply nodded. Dumbledore is paying much more attention to the way I speak than he ever seemed to before. This whole business is odd.

Tom considered before asking, "Can you describe the nature of these incidents?"

Dippet started to speak, "Well Mister Riddle, these childr-"Dumbledore cut him off.

"No, I do not believe we need any help from you, Mister Riddle, thank you though."

Ignoring him, Tom went on. "I'm just saying, there are a certain group of 7th years you may want to look into, if you hadn't considered the obvious yet. This seems like it would be right up their street."

"Yes, well, we will look into that." Dumbledore replied, while Dippet seemed rather confused and displeased.

Tom looked back at Dippet. "May I go then sir? If that's all…"

"Yes, yes, Tom, I believe we have taken up enough of your time, back to your studies then." Dippet escorted Tom to the door.

Tom walked out and the door closed behind him. He considered the curious interrogation as he walked back to his dorm. It wasn't so strange that they investigated the Dark Ritual rumor, but as the squirrels were gone, there was no reason whatsoever to press it. He was, however, insulted that they thought he was behind the scaring of children. My plots are more sophisticated than that! He was starting to become curious, though - what was the purpose or point of scaring first or second years?

The lights in the hallway dimmed slightly as Tom walked past them back down to his dorm. Once there, he slammed the door behind him, hopefully disrupting the sleep of other children.

His whole plan was basically ruined tonight - tonight his actions would be especially watched. He pulled the now useless rings out of the pouch and tossed the lot on his desk.

He sat on the bed, steepling his fingers under his chin. Would they actually be watching him after such a lecture? Wouldn't Dumbledore think he'd been scared into behaving? He was quite irritated that the old man would be so obvious in his distrust in front of Dippet. Unless that's why he was so open in showing me his distrust. To provoke me into doing something…

Tom leapt up, rubbing his forehead in frustration. I certainly have to be more cautious about the man, but there is no reason to get paranoid yet.

It wasn't paranoia that was causing him to pace, it was anger and he couldn't think properly while he was angry.

Bellatrix Black! How many times would that girl drag him through a lake of Fiendfyre? She simply couldn't think properly once given a command. Perhaps I should bind her with a Vow so she never disobeys a direct command again. And then from there on, be very, very specific when telling her what to do...

Of course that was ridiculous. An Unbreakable Vow wouldn't even keep Bellatrix Black under control. The smartest thing to do at this point would be to disregard her completely and never involve her in anything again. Even leaving school wouldn't work; she'd most likely follow him to the ends of the Earth. Fool girl! I should just have her killed!

It wasn't the first time Tom had considered killing Bellatrix Black, but he knew there was a far more appropriate target to take his rage out on.

The goal is not to simply kill the Dark Wizard. The main goal is to find the evidence for Tobo to protect his business.

Tom frowned. But a good fight might help to calm my rage.

Tom smiled as he glanced at the rings on the desk. He had planned to have Tobo enchant them for him. While wearing them on his wand hand he would have had all the extra power and speed he could possibly need. Added to his own natural skills, the fight would be one-sided, and there was no fun in that. No rings, no more help from Tobo. This will end tonight, and I will move on to other affairs.

After dressing for the weather, Tom left his room, then the Slytherin dorm, making sure to close the doors quietly.

Once Tom was out the front door of the school, he pooled his magics to cast the Disillusionment spell, but before he even said the words, a small noise sounded, like the cracking of an egg, and he was invisible. He was slightly surprised, as he'd never been able to cast that wordlessly before.

In fact, before being brought to the Headmaster's, he had been so worn out, but now, Tom was feeling a great deal more powerful than he was that morning, the previous day even. And he knew why.

Powerful wizardry breeds powerful Wizards.

Tom was also aware he was undergoing what was known as "Magical Puberty". A wizard's full potential developed during their teenage years, and their power could take leaps and bounds if they practiced properly.

The Animagus transformation certainly counts as powerful wizardry, but I hadn't expected this large of a boost, nor did I think it would be immediate… I didn't even notice it happening.

Tom was briefly tempted to try some more serious magic and see how strong he really was, but there was plenty of time for that later. Right now, he had a long way to go... and much that could go wrong.

He briefly stopped in the tunnel to make sure this escape bag was in fact still securely hidden, and it was. He considered using the Roadrunner potion to save extra time, but he would be tired when it wore off, and it was better to save it for when it was truly needed.

As soon as he was past the wards, he apparated to a spot in the forest that Tobo had brought him to. Unfortunately, the home of this Wizard would be much harder to find.

Tom touched his wand to his throat and let an incantation pass through his mind, "Sonorous". He felt the spell vibrate down his throat and into his vocal cords, the magic warming his body.

"Brotherss come to me, sspeak with me." The hisses echoed deep into the forest.

He tucked his wand away securely, double-checked that his other tools were secure, and then Tom transformed into a large colorful snake.

He swung his head from side to side, tongue flickering out and tasting the air.

"There iss prey here… Large variety of prey…"

He started slithering off to the east, towards the delicious smell of a very large rodent of some sort, a magical one. Consuming it would make him strong.

"Focuss…" He tried to remember his human motives.

"Brotherss are coming, sspeak with them, sstalk with them."

The many types of delicious edibles around the forest were a distraction, but there was larger prey to hunt.

He slithered around in circles rapidly, trying to coordinate himself; he hadn't had the room to sprawl out the only other time he tried this. Having the body of a snake and most of the mind of a person was proving to be exceedingly difficult.

He focused his mind and the scrap of magic left in him, and closed his eyes.

Things started to become clearer, more coordinated between mind, body and spirit. The urge to hunt rodents diminished and now he had the urge to hunt larger prey, prey that could truly fight back.

Snakes started to arrive by the dozens and circle around him. He looked around in approval and they continued to show up at his side. He waited, until the slithering slowed, and the snakes stopped showing up. There were well over two hundred, closer to three hundred different colored serpents slithering into position, ready to listen to their new master.

He reared up and began to speak. "Brotherss! I sseek one who hidess in your foresst, he iss outssider, and I mean to hunt him."

The snakes hissed among each other and the general consensus was that this man certainly was an outsider; his magic was an inconvenience to the snakes and other creatures - not to mention, he was cruel. They confirmed that he was in fact living in the forest. Where he was, they could not say for sure at the moment; there were rumors and sightings a few days old but nothing concrete yet.

"Sseek for me, sstalk for me and I will reward you brotherss."

So it was done, the snakes would move quickly through the forest, spreading the word and looking for this dark cabin, intruding on them and distressing all the forest animals.

Tom was now sitting in the grass, rather dazed and confused at the moment.

I don't think I needed to sspeak wi- sspe- speak with them as a serpent to get their cooperation, but it's probably better to get used to being a snake.

Tom shook his head to try to get the smell of rats out of his mind; he was aware of how hungry he was now, but he shook it off. This will only become easier.

Tom sat for a few more moments and then rose. It would take time for the serpents to spread the word and locate the wizard's home, and they had assured him they could do it "before pre ssun". Tom had time, if he needed the entire next day he had it. He could explain away his absence by saying he was wandering around the school, or indeed, in bed and overworked. I doubt I will need very long however, my friends seem to be quite capable.

Tom was still sorely tempted to try out some magic now that he had achieved another boost up the power ladder, but it would do no good to draw attention to himself. I have to be very careful not to let my human presence trigger his wards, lest his house relocate one hundred miles east suddenly, or perhaps alert him and have him ambush me.

Instead, Tom sat back on a large stone and watched the stars. He had always appreciated the beauty of the stars.

It was a few hours later when a single snake approached Tom, and then started to slither in the opposite direction again.

"Brother, it iss me," Tom hissed to the retreating serpent.

The snake returned, confused for a moment. It smelled the air with its tongue and eventually agreed that the human Tom was in fact his serpent master as well. The snake informed Tom that the wizard's home was currently about half an hour to the southwest according to the word that was passed along.

Tom thanked the snake, reassured it of his promise, and then promptly transformed into a snake himself once again to follow his brother to the rest of his flock, waiting at the doorstep of this so called dark wizard…

Chapter 7: Tom Riddle and Experience

Chapter Seven – Tom Riddle and Experience

Darius Ahlee watched the dying embers of his fireplace, seated and sipping his cup of evening tea. A rat ran across the mantle, leaped to his bookshelf and sat there for a moment, swinging its head back and forth to sniff the air. He snorted. A home that will protect me from the most dreaded foe! but no protection against minor vermin!

Arcane magic tended to work like that: excellent for one purpose, horribly lacking in other ways. Yet woe to him who dared to tamper with a mage's spellcraft…

Yawning, he stretched upwards out of his chair. His wand was on the couch to his right, but by the time he reached it and turned to dispatch the pest, it had fled.

Darius yawned again, and with some difficulty managed to shuffle to the sink to dispose of his cold tea. The cumbersome weight of his golden amulet almost made him stagger, and forced him to more alertness. Unfortunately, he was not quite alert enough to remember that his wand was not in his robes, and searched futilely till he looked back, where it still sat on the couch.

He sighed, put the dirty cup into the sink and walked straight to bed.

/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*

He was at the head of his pack of brothers, mere feet away from the house.

The house was ancient, created in a time when wizardry was much more powerful and raw. It appeared to be a small run down shack from the outside, but inside it was quite a bit larger and more lavish. No wizard could approach the shack openly without the owner's consent, nor could any long range magic affect it. The protection on it was very heavy indeed.

"Sso heavy that creator didn't bother with other ssecurity meassuress, it sseemss."

The rats he had placed under the Imperius curse while human were able to penetrate the shack, withdraw, and willingly march in the open mouths of his brothers with full enthusiasm. But he didn't dare turn back into a wizard, not yet, and he didn't dare enter the home himself.

He reared up on his tail, nearly six feet high, and turned to his brothers.

"Go, bring him to me," he hissed at his pack, "Do not harm, only impede… Thiss iss my kill…" At that, hundreds of snakes cautiously went forward towards the house.

/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*

Darius Ahlee slept in a dark and chilly bedroom, as was his preference. He lay atop his bed in his sleeping robes, with a brilliant golden chain securely around his throat. His house was a fortress, and his device made him invincible. Darius slept very well indeed - despite the number of enemies he had.

If he didn't sleep so deeply, it was possible that he may have heard the noises: the sounds of soft rustling of the leaves on the roof, quiet scraping coming from several places at once. But then, it was blended into the sounds of the nighttime forest at first; yet it continued, growing louder. Darius turned over in bed once, but never woke to the sounds.

One by one the snakes slithered in through the passages the rats had made, through tunnels in the walls, down the chimney, and out from the ashes of the extinguished fire. Dozens of multicolored serpents of all sizes began to fill the room slowly and quietly, surrounding the bed, and piling up on top of each other.

After only minutes, nearly five hundred snakes were in his room. There wasn't a surface that wasn't covered in several different colored S-shapes, except for his bed, and even that was on the verge of being swallowed by the walls of serpents. Yet they held formation, and waited.

The command came through the air on the wind, a low hiss. "Flussh him out."

/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*

The Dark Wizard Ahlee came out of his front door screaming, swinging his wand around to little effect, tripping and falling over the river of snakes that pushed him forwards.

The largest snake, which had been outside waiting, suddenly transformed into a boy. As his human form took shape a wand, was already in his hand, thrust into the air.

The anti-Apparation ward went up a moment before the house itself vanished, but the man was still there, trying to get an even footing to cast something powerful to destroy the snakes, but failing. It took him a moment to notice that his home had disappeared without him; when it did, his eyes widened in shock.

Tom didn't waste any time. Just as the man started to turn towards him, Tom flicked his left wrist, and the long wooden tube he had made, it flew up his robes and appeared in his hand. As he started to raise it, the Dark Wizard yelled something Tom couldn't make out; the ground beneath him shook so hard he lost his balance and fell. Tom leaned into the fall, tucking and rolling, behind a tree, then back onto his feet.

Interesting, I haven't the slightest clue how he did that… This may be trickier than anticipated.

Tom pressed his wand to the tree, and it exploded in a shower of large foot long splinters. He flung the mass at the man with a wave before running to a new position.

The splinters were not under the class of attacks the man's amulet would dispel, so he had to defend. The man was already protected by some type of shield, clearly keeping the snakes away, but he managed to cast a pyro spell on the mass of sharp stakes flying towards him before he turned his wand on Tom.

Too damn slow!

Tom flicked his wrist at several trees near the man, and each tree fell toward him. The man raised his wand, spun it around, and the trees flew up and back towards Tom, in a wall too wide to dodge.

"Reducto!" Tom yelled and pointed at the ground in front of him. A large patch of soil was blasted loose from the earth. Tom dove into the hole as the trees flew over top of him. He saw a large loose pebble, touched his wand to it, then grabbed the Transfigured grenade, pulling the pin from it and throwing it at the man.

He seemed confused for a moment. Unfamiliar with the Muggle weapon, he hesitated a moment before deciding to repel it back to Tom. It exploded in the air, and the man was apparently startled for a moment by the unexpected blast.

I need to get closer. Tom waved his wand in front of him and yelled "Fumus Parietem!" A thick grey haze appeared between them, obscuring everything. Tom immediately zigged to the left and then zagged towards the man's position. He could feel a curse fly past him as he moved, could hear the man yelling more.

Tom first silently used a Ventriloquo Charm on himself to throw his voice to the far right, and then yelled "Protego Maximus!" A heavy blue shield formed around him. It won't stop his best attacks, but I won't need to.

The man was casting curses in the direction he'd heard Tom's voice, over by dense patch of trees. Tom could make out the blurred jets of light through the haze, and he determined their origin.

Silencio, thought Tom, and his movements were silenced. He started to run up to the man from the other side, but he hadn't gone more than a few feet before the man summoned a wind to blow the conjured haze away. The Dark wizard rounded on Tom, beginning some terrible incantation, so Tom stopped running towards him and simply pointed his wand in his general direction and casually said, "Avada Kedavera!"

The wizard went quiet as the brilliant streak of green light jetted toward him. He tried to dodge, but lost his balance, nearly leaping directly into the path of the miss fired curse and fell to the ground. Tom used this opportunity closer.

As the dark wizard tried to stand, he threw some kind of Dark magical rope at Tom, but Tom simply jumped over the cracking barbed wire and continued, sweeping up a stone from the ground with his wand and Transfiguring it into a dangerous looking yellow gas. Tom had banished the gas away from himself the moment it formed, and it flew towards the dark wizard.

The man jumped up, dropped his current shield to place some sort of Bubblehead charm not just over his head, but his entire body.

Tom took his opportunity and pulled out his blow gun. He raised it to his lips and blew hard. The dart flew through the air faster than the man could register, and it passed through the shield that had saved him from the poison gas. It struck him just under the arm as he was raising his wand. The Muggle tranquilizer worked quickly - the man's words were already slurring as he started to yell something Tom wouldn't have understood.

Suddenly there was nothing but blue light, a brilliant blue light taking up every bit of Tom's perceptions and senses. He couldn't move because he had no body, he couldn't think because he had no mind, he was nothing but blue light. And then nothing.

/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*

Tom woke a short time later, his wand still clutched out of instinct. He immediately rolled a few times and stopped on his back, looking up to get a better view of his surroundings as he swept them with his wand.

Except, it wasn't a wand anymore; it was a mere stick.

Tom didn't stop to consider the trickery. He dropped the unmagical stick and jumped to his feet; the last thing he remembered was blue light as the dark wizard fell unconscious.

It only took him a moment to see that the other wizard was still lying on the ground, asleep.

He looked around: all of the snakes had fled the war zone, there were fallen trees, dying fires, craters and ground that was simply stripped clean, in a great circle around where Tom stood above his fallen foe.

He flicked his wrist to summon his wand from, wherever it was; nothing happened.

WHAT!? Tom thought in a panic, he waved his hand to cast a particularly destructive spell at a tree but the words wouldn't come to him, he didn't even know how to…

Just stop panicking, concentrate. Tom tried to reach out with… And feel it in the air. However he found he was simply staring at the sky.

What is going on?

He walked over to the stick he dropped. Thirteen inches yew, in fact his wand, yet when he picked it up, it felt like nothing other than an ordinary stick.

Tom was trying very hard to supress his panic and remain calm; he had to stay logical and figure out what was going on.

He looked himself over, moved his body around. Other than a few scrapes and some dirt he looked no worse for wear. He closed his eyes and thought of as many details of the battle as he could. It all came to him without hesitation, and he was starting to see the mistakes he had made already, so his mind was intact. Yet that other thing, the indescribable sense of power that coursed through him and the world around him, was gone.

He may have attacked me in some way that depleted all my magic; it will return soon enough... Tom tried to convince himself, but he knew this was something terrible and was kicking himself for taking a moment too long drawing breath to blow the dart. At least the curse used had been interrupted, and therefore underpowered, else he may not.. have survived...

OK, clearly I need to get more serious about this whole immortality thing.

But for now, he needed to try to finish the job. Which would be simple, since it appeared the golden amulet was lying on the ground beside the Dark wizard.

Perfect… I hardly dare look at it without my power, never mind trying to claim it as my own…

Tom took the Dark wizard's wand and snapped it in half over his knee. The sun had not begun to come up yet, and he wasn't thirsty, so he could have only been unconscious for a couple of hours, and the man would be asleep for days yet.

Tom bent over to pull an eight-inch combat knife from a sheath on his boot, and then took another step towards the fallen wizard.

Tom tapped his chin with the tip of the knife, thinking. Even without the wand, a powerful wizard would be difficult to restrain without magic. But if he killed the man, Tobo wouldn't get his information.

Tom sighed and kneeled down before the man, leaned forward with his knife and cut his robes away, using the scraps to tie his arms and legs. When he finished, there was a rather large piece of white cloth left over.

He knew he couldn't spare too much blood; he would have to keep it short and simple.

How does one find a person using five words or less? He sighed in resignation after a moment, and decided he could come up with something better for his own private use later.

For now... Tom took his knife and cut his thumb open.

Of all the things I thought to bring, a quill and parchment never even crossed my mind…

"SOSV5 Reply and follow owl," Tom wrote out in messy, nearly illegible letters with his own blood.

The code was something they had agreed on, and Tobo had assured Tom that he would "rain down an unimaginable tornado of hell" on Tom if he ever used it for anything other than an absolute emergency. Tom was sure that this situation counted as an emergency.

Tom set the letter down to dry.

Now, I just have to find an owl to deliver this… As basically a non-magical person…

Tom knew that even though he could hear owls hooting all around him that not one of them would come to a non-magical person, or deliver their letters, perhaps not even understand them.

As interesting as this new level of difficulty is, I think I prefer approaching my problems with all of my power…

/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*

Once again, Tom tugged on the long thread, and the dead mouse tied to the end seemed to jump under the tree.

The owl over head was clearly interested in it, but Tom knew the owl must think him stupid hiding here in the bush.

Perhaps it's not as smart as I thought. Tom laughed to himself as the large white owl swooped down towards the mouse.

Tom leaped up from his crouching position, stretching out his arms as he jumped, throwing his "net" out at the owl. His cloak flew through the air quickly with the weight of the stones in it. The makeshift net surrounded the owl and brought it down.

Tom pounced on top of it. He wrestled with the cloak and tried to hold it down, but the owl had a surprising amount of fight in it.

"Listen, I understand this is terribly rude…" he said to the struggling mass of cloth. "These are extraordinary circumstances, however… I need your assistance, I need a letter delivered."

The owl was still fighting, and Tom couldn't get a firm grasp to pin it down, nor did he want to be too violent with it. Something told him this was a useless effort; the owl probably didn't even understand the speech of a non-magical person.

"Look, I'll give you an entire bag of Hubbard's Not-so-Ordinary Owl Treats if you just…"

The owl stopped fighting at the mention of the ridiculously expensive snacks.

Tom slapped his forehead. I'm going to pay someone to breed a better species of owl someday, or rather, do it myself so it gets done properly...

Chapter 7.1: Interlude

So here is the real deal.

The last few chapters have been an utter drain; they have turned a leisure activity into a chore.

Simply because the top comment in an early chapter was something like "Tom needs to get some action."

*Oh no, I'm losing them… I won't even scratch the surface for a dozen chapters yet, what am I to do…?* I wondered.

So, I came up with this "defeat a Dark Lord" plot pretty much on the spot. I've tried to wedge this into the established story I have planned (and written to a degree) and it's not going well.

However, within a couple of chapters I will be back on track, and I will pay less attention to the comments, and go at the pace I need to tell the story properly.

This "Interlude" was a way for me to break out from the chore of the current plot and still play in my universe. I had established a great deal of Tom's back story before I even started, so I figured a series of flashbacks would be fun for me to write, and interesting and insightful for you to read.

This is part one of three, each will be more or less the same, a series of flashbacks to Tom's past as a "muggle" with strange powers.

I do have an entire storyline planned for this little mini story; once again the story has sprawled ridiculously. There are a few key events which I want to hit which will help explain why Tom is who he is "now".

This is near 9000 words for part one of this; I'll post it in "mini chapters" over the next couple/few days. You can check back after lunch tomorrow and the next day and find updates, as I don't think I should make a thread every time.

The next "Interlude" will come at an undetermined time, either when I feel it is appropriate to provide context to the story, or when I simply get bored…

I will be taking a break from posting for a while now, but I will be back to writing the main story offline.

Writing and posting one chapter at a time is no good, I need to have 4 or 5 chapters written already when I post, as I did in the beginning. Not only for a quicker pace, but it certainly helps with continuity.

Hope you enjoy meeting a (my parallel universe version of) young Tom Riddle…

(I've made it it's own new story, simply because that's what it has become.)

s/11595761/1/Tom-Riddle-Origins-of-a-Dark-Lord

Chapter 8

Chapter Eight

With his legs wrapped around the dark wizard's torso, Tom was quite uncomfortable, seated as he was on the damp forest floor, his left hand holding the man's head back, and his right hand holding his knife to the man's throat, to be drawn the moment he awoke. Hopefully Tobo Mott would appear before that was necessary, but Riddle didn't have much of an option, with his magic having been depleted. As it was, he would have to rely on his senses of hearing and touch to discern consciousness.

Even if Tobo does hurry, and he is able to restore me to power I will still have to explain my absence from school…At the worst possible time, right after…

Suddenly, it came to him.

Oh, of course…That's a simple explanation that nobody can argue with.It will even account for me being at less than full strength if I need recovery time.

The pressure in the back of his mind began to fade, but there was still the matter of figuring out exactly what had happened to him and how to undo it.

Perhaps when Tobo arrives we can strip this "dark wizard" of his magic and impregnate it into me… is that even possible? Tobo should at least know of a way to restore my strength.

If not... Tom looked over at the unconscious form of the wizard he had cast down at his own expense... One person knew what had been done, and could perhaps undo it.

I have a knife to his throat, and he has a vast ocean of invisible force to stop me in ways I can't comprehend. And then, what if Tobo decides to kill two birds with one stone?

Yet there was nobody else to trust. Bellatrix? A slim chance, but there was no possible way he would let her see him like this. Slughorn - Slughorn would help him if he'd lost his powers at school, but Tom didn't want to push him for this.

On the other hand...

It would take a very convincing story, and evidence to accompany it, to explain this to Albus Dumbledore. Part of the truth should work, and the old man would surely want to help, to satisfy his curiosity if for no other reason.

It was an option, not a very good one, but perhaps in the most extreme case Tom would have to try it.

He hadn't truly considered that he may never have his power again; anything magic could do could be undone as well if you approached it from the right angle. Wizards didn't even know how to properly use magic, there was always an angle, some unseen connection that would act like gravity and draw things together.

But right now, such a loss! Magic surged through the world all around him. On every breeze, in the flow of the stream, in the sunlight and even air itself- the feeling was normally tangible. Yet just now it was all non-existent to him.

I was so sure of my plan that the idea never entered my mind…Too worked up in the moment and I ran in without a real plan.I need to learn more patience…

He had lived as a Muggle when he was young, and it didn't suit him. The moment he had first felt that incredible force pressing on him was the first time he had ever felt alive. Surely, it wasn't lost to him for good?

Suddenly, there was something. It was faint, but it was there, it was approaching him.

Tom leaned back and used the dark wizard's body as a shield to protect himself from whatever was coming towards him.

He forced his eyes open and watched as the silvery white glow of a floating white squid appeared from thin air and drifted towards him. It was floating through the air, propelling itself with long silvery tentacles, and emitting magic like heat from a fire.

If I can see it, and feel it…

Tom couldn't produce a Patronus himself, and for that matter he had never expected Tobo to be able to create one either. Usually, the spell didn't induce any feelings like the "joy" and "happiness" that others claimed to be filled with. This time, however, the white glow of the magic washed over Tom like waves of relief. He could feel himself relaxing, yet he held tight to the dark wizard.

Tom knew what the squid was, and could just barely feel it, but other than that, the world remained in black and white. There was no mistaking what this was, or who had sent it - only one explanation for that.

"If it's an emergency we don't have time for this owl nonsense. My Patronus will bring me your location and I will be there immediately, ready for combat." The rough voice of Tobo Mott echoed from the squid as it floated there.

"Wait!" he exclaimed, hoping the Patronus could understand and comply. It didn't leave yet, but floated like a ghost, mere meters away from Tom.

A patronus is literally a projection of a person's magic, and something else...Has anybody experimented with what else a patronus is capable of doing, other than keep dementors at bay?

He had never had enough experience with the spell or the inclination to look further.

Tom focused on the magic squid; he closed his eyes and let everything it radiated wash over him. He could feel that unmistakeable magic heating up the air as the light of it lit up the surroundings. Tom tried to feel it elsewhere, but failed. There was magic yet in the world, right in front of him.

If I only reach out and touch it.Grab hold, as I first did when I was young…

Tom put the knife back in its sheath and unwrapped himself from his fallen foe, focused on more important matters. He stood and walked towards the ghostly form. "Tell Tobo Mott…" he whispered when he was quite close, "I hope this works!" Tom shouted in desperation, as he jumped forward with his arms and mental focus extended. He tried to grab the force within the squid and take it as his own.

The squid vanished and Tom once again lost consciousness.

/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*

Tobo Mott waited in his heavily warded basement for his Patronus to project the location of battle to him.

"He sends an owl… Of a thousand ways to communicate he goes with an owl… Either it's bad, or he's got a dose of Bahl's Stupefaction…" Tobo was not pleased to be dragged into an emergency situation with no details or prep time. "I should have known better… The kid should have never been involved in this plot in the first place; in over his head he was…" the man muttered to himself as he double-checked that his armour was securely fitted.

"Who knows what the hell I'm walking into now… never should've listened to him. Prob'ly a huge mess to clean up here, else Tom went and put an end to his own story somehow." Tobo's voice was growing louder as he spoke to himself, stretching his wand arm to warm it up. The tea kettles on the mantle, which he had enchanted to feel fear, began to steam and whistle loudly.

The moment the Patronus returned, he knew something was off.

The yellow and orange flickers of light on the stone walls drained of color and the world became black and white for a moment before the Patronus grew in intensity, washing the entire room with a silver glow and restoring color before it disappeared again.

Tobo Mott lost consciousness.

/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*/*

Darius Ahlee stirred but did not wake; the tranquilizer was starting to wear off, and the cloth that bound him would not be a hindrance once he awoke. Yet Tom Riddle was still sprawled on the ground a few feet away, in no position to detain the wizard: the boy was lying there as though he were dead.

He was in murky green water that stretched as far as the eye could see.He was struggling to swim as the waves bounced him up and down; the vast force of the sea was trying to overcome him.He was fighting it, trying to use the force to help himself rather than let it swallow him.Every wave that crashed down on his head pushed him further under. He was losing his ability to fight, and much worse, he was losing his will to fight.

A hot sharp pain cut through the dream and woke Tom. Instinctively, he rolled away from the pain and tried to jump up, but he found himself lacking the energy to cleanly spring himself off the ground. Instead he flopped over, out of breath.

"I don't think I could have snuck up on you like that unless you were hurt, or if I was walking into a trap. Am I walking into a trap?" Tobo's voice came from behind him.

"Would you trust me to tell you if it was?" Tom asked casually; he couldn't show Tobo any more weakness than he had to. Difficult, considering he was struggling to continue sitting up straight at the moment.

Tobo scoffed at that, "Not bloody likely, but I trust my senses and it seems to me you're a Muggle."

Tom felt his temper flare at the word. "I may not have a wand, but I have a knife."

"And a big mouth, which is a second away from having a wand shoved in it."

Tom was about to retort when he realized he'd probably better just be quiet.

Tobo continued as though Tom hadn't started. "Now, first of all… Stupefy!" Tom felt the heat as the red jet flew over his shoulder and struck the poorly bound dark wizard.

"Secondly…" Tobo said as he lowered his wand a little to aim at Tom's chest, "Just what did you do to my Patronus? It made me fall over."

Tom gestured towards the stunned wizard behind him, "Apparently this one did something to strip me of my magic as he fell. I found myself without my power, for a time."

Tobo lifted Tom off the ground a couple of feet and slammed him back down. "That was obvious. What did you do to my Patronus?"

Tom found himself slightly winded by the slam, but he caught his breath long enough just to give a quick laugh and reply "I ate it!"

Chapter 10

Chapter 10

Tom would have liked to spend some of his idle time practicing his magic, but as he was in the Infirmary for magical exhaustion, his wand was being kept well away except for one hour after supper, under the watchful eye of a nurse. Tom did manage to find some amusement in subtly knocking over Lucius Bode's water glass across the aisle from him whenever the boy tried to reach for it.

Natural skills aside, knowledge had played a large part in carving the depths of his well of power. The proper book was even more useful than a wand in some cases.

Tom dug out an old book he had neglected for too long. He was sure he could remember most by memory, but he knew all too well how faulty memory really was. Besides, there are always lines between the lines.

Ancient Secrets, By Marwyn the Mage. Tom affectionately stroked the cover. Of course right now it appeared to be The Fungi You Never Knew! with a bright green cover and a clean look to it.

In his second year Tom had stolen this copy off of a used bookshelf in a section of Knockturn Alley that Dumbledore had forbidden him to enter. That had been the main reason Tom had decided to investigate.

The cover was particularly worn, even for an old book. Where it had been torn or deformed, it appeared as though there were blood stains on the black cover from the "wounds". It looked as though it had been read thousands of times, over hundreds of years, but simple diagnostic spells had revealed the book was enchanted in some way to appear old and forgotten, as well as impervious to normal harms. Tom assumed Fiendfyre or a number of other curses may destroy it, though he had no intention of trying.

The fact that somebody thought nothing of enchanting perhaps dozens of these books with permanent powerful magic just for effect was enough to tell Tom that this "Marwyn" knew a few things about wizardry that Tom could appreciate.

Not only that, but the readings of Marwyn sometimes contradicted the work of "magical scholars" from the Ministry-mandated reading list in the exact ways Tom had disagreed with them from the start.

That was probably why Bellatrix had been unable to find a copy even in the forbidden section of the library.

Tom had decided to make this book one of the main topics of his own classes once he came into power in the school. It would be no fun being the most powerful wizard if the second best was miles behind.

Some of these children actually do have potential, but they won't realize it studying at Hogwarts right now…

The book strongly recommended the use of non-verbal magic and that was something Tom had used before he knew wizards existed.

Marwyn claimed that by using traditional incantations you were relying on the natural magic of the world to power you for the most part - external fuel. Whereas if you developed enough internal power through practice, you would not need the keys of wand work and incantations to open the external doors, but if you did use them, they appeared far more effective. That had resonated with Tom the first time he read it, and he felt like it was more relevant now than ever.

I didn't start with flamboyant wand work and strange phrases, and even when they tried to teach me, it never suited me.

Tom chuckled at the idea of showing his Charms Professor this book. Any Professor would probably chuck the thing, and tell the Headmaster he was looking into the Dark Arts, besides. Marwyn did, after all, speak of the usefulness of sacrifices, and never shied away from any type of magic, no matter its source.

The first few chapters were about the fundamental workings of magic, and the next few on the different levels and channels of magic that can be accessed. The author also went into great detail on the different theories of magic's origin, none of which he actually agreed with.

The rest of the book described in vivid detail Marwyn's educated speculation on the events that occurred in places like magical Italy, The Arm of Dorne, and Atlantis itself after the unpracticed use of the most powerful forces.

Tom had decided that if the author put such emphasis on the dangers of true magic, then it was best to set aside until he had read many more books like this one. There was one in particular, another written by Marwyn which he mentioned once, The Book of Lost Books. Tom had never been able to find a copy, and he had truly looked.

Tom closed the book after a time and pushed it aside. He then opened the drawer that held his wand (hadn't it been locked? Tom couldn't remember anymore) and looked it over. There was an energy coming from it, even without touching it, he could feel it.

A crutch… I've only needed it for certain things, none of which I expect to encounter in the next few days.

Tom knew he was already at a disadvantage, weak.

Other than "Battle Magic" on Thursday I see no reason to need to perform any extraordinary magic, and even then I can beat Chang in a number of other ways… Although, perhaps putting forth an actual effort would be beneficial.

If he had to relearn magic and grow strong again, he would do it the same way he did in the beginning. No wand or words unless he absolutely needed them.

So he resigned himself to putting it in his holster and committing to not use it for trivial things.

After lunch was served and consumed Tom then decided he should take this chance to talk with MacNair. He was getting tired of sitting around like a lump while there were things to be looked into.

Either his girlfriend is spreading terrible rumors about him, or she is betraying his dark secrets. Either way she should be punished… And I need to know if I can still rely on him or not.

Ever since Tom had heard that MacNair had taken the House Elf ban to heart, he had been worried.

The MacNair that Tom thought he knew wouldn't become friends with an elf… If the rumor was true then MacNair's ability for deception was worrying, and Tom would need to find out exactly what else the boy had been lying about.

As Tom was leaving the old nurse Chloe came running over to him, "Oh Tom! You must lie down; you are in no condition to go back to class."

Tom gave her a wide smile, "Ah Chloe, you are sweet. You remind me of my grandmother. Will you force feed me an entire batch of cookies as well?"

Chloe tittered, "Maybe I should, chocolate is always good for magical exhaustion."

"Trust me, my sweet tooth won't allow less than five candy bars in my dorm at any time," Tom replied swiftly.

"Oh well… OK. You HAVE to remain in bed Tom though, no gallivanting around chasing after girls."

Tom legitimately laughed, "No fear on that account Chloe, that's the last thing on my mind."

The nurse smiled slyly at him. "Oh yes, indeed, that's why I wouldn't let Miss Black in to see you while you were napping, though she tried twice."

Tom sighed. The last thing he needed was Bellatrix making him look suspicious. "I will avoid Miss Black at all costs!" Tom told her with emphasis as he started to walk away.

The nurse said something to him as he was leaving, but he was thinking of other things already and simply waved back at her.

Tom knew MacNair had a spare period right now, and suspected he would be in the library. Unfortunately, it was highly likely that David Monroe would be there too, since the boy treated the library as a social club rather than an archive of knowledge.

Not that Monroe was an actual threat to Tom, magic or no, but he was still an absurd annoyance at the best of times.

Eventually Tom decided that not only did he need to speak with MacNair about elves, he also had to learn what he could about the "Monsters in the night". And he couldn't very well do that unless he socialized with other students.

Perhaps when I regain all of my previous power I will transform myself again and slither through the pipes in the walls and listen in on conversations, rather than having to participate in them…

Just as soon as he had walked around the corner of the Hospital wing, Bellatrix was on him.

"Where have you been the last few days? You missed so much!" She said in an odd tone.

"I doubt I've missed anything significant. Don't play games with me, Bellatrix," Tom said as he locked into her gaze, annoyed with her for trying to pry into his business in the Hospital Wing. She wavered and looked down after a moment.

"I just mean, I don't know…" she replied slowly.

"Of course not. That is why I never asked you."

"Huh?" The girl replied with a puzzled look.

"Quite right." Tom said, finishing that line of conversation. "Tell me, have you seen MacNair?"

"Not lately. Should I find him for you?" Bellatrix asked, a bright look in her eyes.

"No, you should find your dorm room and confine yourself." Tom turned and walked away.

I need to come up with a way to keep her well away from me until I need her, I have just as many problems as I like to deal with at the moment and her adding more might just make me lose my composure.

When Tom got to the library he was pleased not only that MacNair was in fact in the room, but there was also a glaring absence of David Monroe and his entourage.

Tom started making his way over to his questionable ally when the oaf Hagrid came around the bookshelf and bumped into Tom, knocking him over.

"Eh, sorry 'bout that Tom, didn't see yeh there." The half giant offered in apology along with his hand.

Tom paid no attention to the hand but instead pushed himself up. "It's my fault really; you're larger and thicker than a castle wall. If I didn't see you lumbering along, that's my own shame." Tom said it coldly, but the oaf seemed to take no notice to the insult.

"Alright Tom, I'll cya." He walked toward the door with a large book that looked extremely tiny in his hands.

He's just stupid; literally half-human. I shouldn't blame him for his idiocy.

Yet Tom did blame him. He found himself suddenly wanting to hurt the boy named Hagrid for knocking him down as if he were a fly.

One problem at a time now… The oaf will probably get himself sent to Azkaban for trying to raise a dragon or the like soon enough.

MacNair was in a position where he clearly had seen Tom get bulldozed, but he had pretended not to notice.

"Hello MaNair, what are you reading there?" Tom asked in a friendly voice.

MacNair pretended to be startled, as though he was absorbed in the book and hadn't noticed Tom.

The boy showed Tom the page he was reading. There was a large, very detailed moving picture of a goblin cutting a wizards throat from behind.

"Exciting," Tom said as he watched the spray of blood from the wizard's throat.

"Bloody disgusting if you ask me." MacNair was already starting to get worked up, Tom could use that.

This interrogation would be easy and gentle. "Surely you don't mean the violence or blood, Macnair. Unless I am highly mistaken I believe it was you who slew that centaur last year." Tom paused to watch his expression, and was pleased to see a studied look of blankness. "That was rather impressive, the cover-up after, I mean. The actual deed did get the Headmaster's attention, which is never to be desired you know."

MacNair seemed a little alarmed that Tom knew. "Well… I suppose I should have known you would see through it…" He took a settling breath, then went on, "It wasn't like I set out to kill it, it got in the way of-"

Tom cut him off, "I do not care that it was done, or why you did it."

"Oh."

"Anyway, what do you mean, disgusting?" Tom inquired, tapping the book.

"I mean, you can't trust a single magical creature as far as you can throw them, and you can throw some of them pretty damn far. I know from experience." MacNair looked down and frowned.

"I imagine you are referring to your House Elf? What was his name?" Tom probed lightly.

"Oscar. Yes, his betrayal is what got me thinking about how we can't trust any of them."

Tom smiled. "Not unless you have put them under an over-powered Dark curse."

MacNair had a smile to return for that comment, but it faded. "I mean, really. Oscar was magically bound to my house above all, just because he came to Hogwarts doesn't mean that Dippet's ridiculous orders should take priority over my own."

Tom stood and listened, the silence would force him to continue.

"It was the elf's choice," MacNair said confidently. "They do have some wiggle room for choice, and Oscar chose the bloody school over me."

Tom frowned as though in empathy, but really he was disappointed. It sounded like the boy had a real bond with the creature, which was very strange to Tom. "You sound like you lost a friend." Tom tried to sound sympathetic when he said it. He never could tell if he pulled that one off properly.

MacNair was certainly insulted now, that was plain. "You think he was my friend? He was my servant, bound to me. I didn't lose a friend; I was played and betrayed by the creature!" He spat out.

Tom would have warmed up to MacNair at that statement, if he hadn't been so passionate about it.

"Listen, Walden. If you're interested in learning about animal betrayal, I have read a few good books that are related. I can come up with a list for you."

MacNair perked up. "Yeah, that would be great, Tom."

Tom didn't know which books would serve MacNair's interest best, but there were few that would serve his own if MacNair took them to heart. He idly wondered if he could set MacNair on Hagrid, but decided to get to the other topic of interest instead. "Let me ask you, what do you know of an apparent monster running around the school at night?"

MacNair shrugged. "I know there are a bunch of scared kids saying there's a monster."

"Do you believe it?"

MacNair shrugged again. "Sounds to me like somebody is having some fun. Or it's just a bunch of rumors. Remember how everybody thought that the Perks girl was crushed by the moving staircase?"

Tom simply said, "Oh, yes, Dippet did say she changed schools to Beauxbaton."

Though I have my doubts…

Tom wasn't sure if MacNair was being completely honest, but it wasn't worth risking prying into his mind. If he detected it, some of the trust Tom had built with him would disappear.

If he was in on this affair, I expect he would have told me in order to get some advice.

Tom stood up and walked away without saying goodbye; MacNair didn't seem to mind.

As he left the library he heard a familiar voice coming down the hallway.

Well isn't that just perfect timing…

David Monroe came around the corner with a girl on his arm; he was whispering in her ear and hadn't seen Tom yet. He briefly squashed a desire to run as cowardly, although he certainly wasn't interested in a confrontation. Usually the only way to avoid such with Monroe was to avoid him completely, since there was nothing about him that Tom could appreciate or respect.

He started walking towards the couple in order to make his way back to the common room.

David finally did notice Tom then and when he did he stopped short for a moment before putting on an overly enthusiastic smile. "Tom! You had us all so very worried; there were rumors that you had been taken off to be kissed by the Dementors!"

Tom had meant to keep this casual, but the mention of Dementors had rattled him a little bit.

When he spoke his voice was much colder than he had intended it to be, "You should know better than to listen to rumors, Monroe. Just this morning a gossiping nurse told me a rumor that you were caught in a storeroom with Alice Aubry the night before last. Yet here you are with Sam… Something… You see how unreliable rumors can be?" He finished with a dry smile and looked at the girl who was staring at him; Tom nodded to confirm his story to her.

The girl suddenly pulled away from David with a shocked look and stared through him.

"What? Don't listen to him, he's lying Sam!" David said rather pathetically as he looked at her shoe's.

The girl either had some common sense or Legilimency training, because she slapped David and ran off down the hallway, crying.

Tom smiled at that.

"Samantha wait, I can explain!" Monroe yelled after her, but she was gone. When David turned back to Tom he was surprised, he had never seen that look in the boy's eyes, but he recognized it, having seen it in his mirror too many times to count: Intent to kill. He was shocked beyond all telling, as Monroe never really seemed to take his affaires seriously. Apparently the bloody fool actually gave a damn about this one; Tom could feel magic building in the air a tangible pressure in the hallway.

It had been stupid to think they could cross paths without some sparks flying; the boy just couldn't seem to help himself when it came to antagonizing Tom.

"Now David, surely you aren't thinking of doing something foolish?" Tom said in his most bored voice. "Foolishness would be you doing anything other than going along on your way."

"Would it be foolish, Riddle? It seems to me you are not quite yourself today…" It was almost as though heat was radiating off of Monroe now as starting to reach into his robes.

Of course, he senses I'm weak. Tom started to feel magic flowing through the air towards Monroe like a light breeze.

If Tom had his strength he would have snuffed out Monroe's little ember, and shown him how to truly assert dominance, by blasting the boy through one of the schools ancient walls. The arrogance was too much for him. Of course, if he'd had strength, Monroe wouldn't have dared to threaten him, the bully.

Tom looked over David's shoulder and said loudly, "Hello! Professor Dumbledore! How are you?" The boy's hand froze in his pocket as he stopped to turn and look.

"Accio boots!" Tom said quietly as he brandished his wand at David's feet.

The boots came flying off, pulling David's legs out from under him and causing him to crash down onto the floor. Tom dodged the incoming boots and swiftly moved forward as David was trying to get up. A swift kick to the sternum winded the boy and knocked him back flat on the floor. As he was gasping for breath Tom stomped on the boy's hand which was still clutching his wand and it rolled out across the floor.

In a smooth motion Tom turned and swooped down on David, pressing his own wand to the boy's forehead. "Somnium." The light faded from David's wide eyes as they closed.

If Tom had a little more power at the moment, he may have hovered David up to the high ceiling and stuck him there and put a silence ward over him, so people would walk past him all day and never notice him trapped and yelling for help.

If it wouldn't result in expulsion Tom would take Monroe's wand and snap it. There probably were ways around the detection charms the administration would use to see if it had been intentional, but nothing came to mind in the moment.

This will suffice for now, I suppose, just a little lesson, a prelude to the real lesson, Tom thought as he kicked the unconscious boy in the stomach.

There was no point getting into any real trouble at the moment, so Tom decided to put the idea aside for now and come up with something creative at his leisure. It would have to be something that Tom couldn't be blamed for and it had to go beyond simple pain or fear, something to truly scar the boy.

I always enjoy a chance to practice teaching lessons.